Henry Shapiro Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Henry Shapiro Papers 1920-1992 1931-1973
MSS82704
Shapiro, Henry, 1906-1991
51,500 items
151 containers plus 1 oversize
61.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Journalist. Correspondence, wire service reports, reference files, speeches and writings, and personal files pertaining to Henry Shapiro's career and writings as chief correspondent in the Moscow bureau of United Press International from the 1930s to the 1970s.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilʹich, 1906-1982.; Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016.; Ceaușescu, Nicolae.; Cronkite, Walter. Walter Cronkite papers.; Daniloff, Nicholas, 1934- --Correspondence.; Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeevich, 1894-1971.; Kádár, János, 1912-1989.; Lyons, Eugene, 1898-1985. Eugene Lyons papers.; Shapiro, Henry, 1906-1991.; Shapiro, Henry, 1906-1991. L.U.R.S.S. après Staline. 1954.; Stalin, Joseph, 1878-1953.
Organizations
United Press International.
Subjects
Aeronautics--Soviet Union.; Agriculture--Soviet Union.; Civil rights.; Cold War.; Education.; Elections--Soviet Union.; Espionage--Soviet Union.; Foreign correspondents--Russia (Federation)--Moscow.; International relations.; Jews--Migrations.; Jews--Soviet Union.; Science--Soviet Union.; Trials--Soviet Union.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
Places
China--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Cuba--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--Economic conditions.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--China.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Cuba.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations.; Soviet Union--History--German occupation, 1941-1944.; Soviet Union--History.; Soviet Union--Politics and government.; Soviet Union--Social conditions.; Soviet Union--Social life and customs.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.
Occupations
Journalists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Henry Shapiro, journalist and Moscow correspondent, were given to the Library of Congress in 1994, 1996, and 1998 by his wife, Ludmilla Shapiro.
Additional Guides
A description of the Shapiro Papers appears in Library of Congress Acquisitions: Manuscript Division, 1994-1995, pp. 38-39.
Transfers
Sound recordings of interviews and lectures have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of this collection.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Henry Shapiro are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1906, Apr. 19 Born, Vaslui, Romania
1920 Emigrated to United States
1928 Naturalized United States citizen
1929 A.B., College of the City of New York, New York, N.Y.
1932 J.D., Harvard University Law School, Cambridge, Mass.
1933 Studied at Moscow Law Institute, Moscow, USSR
1934 1937 Moscow correspondent, New York Herald Tribune, Morning Post of London, and Reuters of London
1937 1973 Chief correspondent and manager of Moscow bureau, United Press International
1937 Married Ludmilla Nikitina
1942 First American correspondent to file an eyewitness report from the Battle of Stalingrad
1953 First westerner to report Joseph Stalin's death
1954 Published L'U.R.S.S. après Staline (n.p.: Gallimard. 254 pp.)
1955 Nieman Fellow, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1962 1963 Visiting lecturer, University of California, Berkeley, Calif.
1973 Retired from United Press International and moved to Madison, Wis.
1973 1979 Kemper K. Knapp professor and adjunct professor, University of Wisconsin School of Journalism, Madison, Wis.
1991, Apr. 4 Died, Madison, Wis.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Henry Shapiro (1906-1991) span the years 1920-1992 with most of the material concentrated between 1931 and 1973. The collection focuses principally on Shapiro's long career as United Press International's chief Moscow correspondent and bureau manager. Present during the regimes of Joseph Stalin, Nikita Khrushchev, and Leonid Brezhnev, Shapiro reported on a range of issues pertaining to Soviet society as well as many of the major events which shaped East/West relations during this period. The papers include wire service reports, reference files, correspondence, articles, lectures, a memoir, notes, and personal files organized in five series: Personal File, United Press International (UPI) Moscow Bureau, Speeches and Writings File, Additions, and Oversize. The collection includes English and Russian language material.
The Personal File provides a biographical profile of Shapiro based on correspondence, scrapbooks, clippings, photographs, and other material. Correspondence in the series is primarily with friends and colleagues concerning visits and travel plans. Other letters pertain to arrangements for lectures and issues related to publishing Shapiro's articles. The scrapbooks include material pertaining to his entire career as well as numerous felicitations on his retirement in 1973.
Shapiro's files from the United Press International Moscow Bureau constitute the heart of the collection. Shortly after arriving in Moscow in 1933 and briefly studying Soviet law, Shapiro became a correspondent for Reuters of London and the New York Herald Tribune. In 1937 he was hired by UPI and was appointed manager of its Moscow bureau in 1939. He retained that position until his retirement in 1973, concluding an unusually long career in a world capital in which foreign correspondents typically had much shorter periods of duty.
The Administrative File of the Moscow Bureau series reflects the organizational and financial aspects of the bureau documented in correspondence and memoranda regarding assignments, arrangements for interviews, and communications with other UPI offices and personnel. The file also includes financial records and contracts with Soviet personnel.
The Reference File includes Russian language newspaper clippings, printed matter, notes, and wire service reports pertaining to virtually every aspect of Soviet life and society. Because contact with many typical news sources was not available to Western reporters, Soviet newspapers and magazines were an important source of supplemental information and background material. Whitman Bassow, a UPI Moscow correspondent in the 1950s, notes in his book The Moscow Correspondents that "the key to comprehensive reporting was always the clipping file from the Soviet press and magazines and notes compiled by reporters." * Notable and extensive material in the Reference File pertains to agriculture, trials during the 1930s, biographies, Jews and Jewish emigration from the Soviet Union, elections, espionage, and the regime of Nikita Khrushchev. Foreign relations are documented by considerable material regarding Soviet relations with the United States and China. Files pertaining to China contain many reports on the deterioration of Sino-Soviet relations during the early 1960s.
* Bassow, Whitman, The Moscow Correspondents (New York: W. Morrow, c.1988), 299.
The Wire Service Reports in the UPI series were filed by the Moscow Bureau from 1931 to 1971. Although there are numerous gaps, the reports provide a comprehensive account of the Soviet Union during that time. The reports were often rewritten and shortened by editors in the United States, adding to the historical significance of the copies retained by Shapiro. There are a few incoming cable and telegraph messages from UPI's New York office from 1946 to 1948, but the file is primarily composed of the Moscow bureau's outgoing stories. Eugene Lyons, a predecessor of Shapiro's at UPI and an early Soviet sympathizer who left the Soviet Union in disillusionment in 1934, wrote many of the reports from 1931 to 1933. Reports from the mid-1930s cover social and economic conditions, foreign policy, political struggles, scientific advances, and aeronautical achievements. Events leading up to Germany's invasion of Russia are chronicled from 1939 through the summer of 1941. Reports are absent for 1942-1945, but resume in 1946 with many written by Walter Cronkite, who served as a UPI correspondent from 1946 to 1948. Shapiro was one of the few American reporters who remained in Moscow as the Cold War intensified during the late 1940s and early 1950s. Reports during the 1950s and 1960s are fairly complete and reflect the heightened tensions between the USSR and the United States. Prominent topics during this period include the rise and fall of Nikita Khrushchev, internal Soviet politics, the breakdown of relations with China, Fidel Castro and Cuba, the exploration of outer space, economic and domestic policies, Leonid Brezhnev's ascent to power, and the Viet Nam conflict.
The Speeches and Writings File contains drafts and printed copies of Shapiro's articles and drafts and newspaper serializations of his book, L'U.R.S.S. après Staline. Also included are interviews with Nikita Khrushchev (1957), Hungary's János Kádár (1966), and Nicolae Ceausescu (1972). After retiring from UPI, Shapiro continued to travel and lecture on the Soviet Union, and his files contain lecture notes and other related material. Other files include notes on détente, politics, and ideology, and a transcript of Shapiro's memoir recorded by the American Jewish Committee.
Addition I supplements the collection with correspondence, reference files, wire service reports, and speeches and writings files. The correspondence is composed chiefly of personal letters from professional colleagues and friends, including journalist Nicholas Daniloff during the early 1980s, and copies of some of Shapiro's letters. Reference files contain background material pertaining to Russian leaders, civil rights, education, and international incidents. The speeches and writings file includes draft articles, book projects, interviews, and material related to Shapiro's lecture schedule. Wire service reports relate primarily to relations between the United States and the Soviet Union during the 1960s. Noteooks in Addition II include handwritten notes from press conferences and interviews with Soviet officials as well as observations on conditions in the Soviet Union.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in five series:
Personal File, 1939-1992
United Press International, Moscow Bureau, 1920-1973
Speeches and Writings File, 1937-1987
Additions, 1931-1990
Oversize, 1954
Container List
- Personal File, 1939-1992 (Box 1-3)
  Correspondence, biographical material, clippings, photographs, scrapbooks, and miscellany.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Art collection, 1973-1984, undated (Box 1)
  - Biographical material, 1960-1991, undated
  - Calling cards, undated
  - Clippings, 1944-1992, undated, (2 folders)
  - Contracts, 1954, 1972
  - Correspondence
    - 1942-1972, (8 folders)
    - 1973-1992, undated, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Invitations, 1962-1977, undated, (2 folders)
  - Korotich, Vitaly, 1977, 1987, undated
  - Miscellany, 1960-1974, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1954-1981, undated, (4 folders)
  - Scrapbooks, 1939-1973, (4 folders)
  - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr, in the United States, 1975, undated
- United Press International, Moscow Bureau, 1920-1973 (Box 4-133)
  - Administrative File, 1954-1973 (Box 4-5)
    Correspondence, financial records, and newsletters.
    Arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein.
    - Contracts with Soviet personnel, 1966-1969, undated (Box 4)
    - Correspondence
      - 1954-1969, (9 folders)
      - 1970-1973, undated, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Financial records, 1966-1971, undated, (4 folders)
    - Internal newsletters, 1957-1973, undated, (2 folders)
  - Reference File, 1920-1973 (Box 6-25)
    Clippings, printed matter, notes, wire service reports, and miscellany.
    Arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - Abortion, 1936-1937, undated (Box 6)
    - Aeronautics
      - Civil, 1937-1938, undated
      - Defense, 1935
      - Dirigibles, 1931-1935, undated
      - Long-distance flights, 1933-1937, undated
      - Osoaviakhim (Society for Air and Chemical Defense), 1935-1936, undated
      - Parachutes, 1937, undated, 1935-1936, undated
      - Sports, 1935-1936, undated
      - Stratosphere, 1934-1938, undated
    - Agricultural exhibition, 1939, undated
    - Agriculture
      - Collective farms, 1930-1937, undated
      - Cotton, 1935-1939, undated
      - Crops, 1935
      - Flax, 1931-1937, undated
      - General, 1927-1953, undated, (6 folders); (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - Grain, 1931, undated
      - Livestock, 1932-1938, undated
    - Alcohol, 1937, undated
    - Alimony, 1935-1936
    - Amenities, 1937, undated
    - Anglo-American School, Moscow, 1934-1935
    - Animals and birds, 1954-1970
    - Architecture, 1934-1937, undated
    - Arctic regions
      - General, 1934-1939, undated
      - Northeast passage, 1933-1934, undated
    - Armed forces, 1930-1947, undated, (3 folders)
    - Art, 1930-1957, undated
    - Artels, 1935, undated
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1934-1935, undated
    - Baltic Sea, 1939-1944 (Box 8)
    - Bazaars, 1932-1937
    - Bibliographies, 1930-1931, undated
    - Biographies
      - Architects, 1937, undated
      - Armed forces, 1935-1938, undated
      - Chubar, Vlas Yakovlevich, undated
      - Engineers, 1937-1938, undated
      - Industrialists, 1937-1938, undated
      - Kaganovitch, Lazar M. and Maria, 1933-1940, undated
      - Kalinin, Mikhail Ivanovitch, 1935-1940, undated
      - Khrushchev, Nikita See Container 17, same heading
      - Miscellaneous, 1932-1948, undated, (4 folders)
      - Molotov, Vyacheslav M., and Polina Semenova Zhemchujina, 1938-1940, undated
      - People's Commissariat of Internal Affairs (NKVD), 1937-1938, undated
      - Politicians, 1937-1940, undated (Box 9)
      - Pushkin, Aleksandr S., undated
      - Scientists, 1937-1941, undated
      - Stalin, Joseph See Container 21, same heading
      - Trotsky, Leon See Container 23, same heading
      - Tukhachevski, Mikhail, 1935
      - Voroshilov, Kliment Yefremovitch, 1935-1941, undated
      - Women, 1932-1947, undated
    - Birth rate, 1937
    - Bureaucracy, 1932-1937
    - "B" miscellaneous, 1935-1936, undated
    - Cable and telephone rates, 1935, undated
    - Census, 1937-1939, undated
    - Children, 1930-1935, undated
    - Citizens' rights, undated
    - Communist International, 1928-1937, undated
    - Communist party
      - Central Committee Plenum, 1937-1938, undated, (2 folders)
      - General, 1933-1967, undated
    - Competition under socialism, 1935, undated
    - Comsomols, 1937, undated
    - Constitution, 1936-1937, undated
    - Crime, 1934-1961, undated
    - Cultural development, 1934, undated
    - "C" miscellaneous, 1931-1935, undated
    - Distinguished visitors, 1931-1938
    - "D" miscellaneous, 1931-1935, undated
    - Editorials in Soviet press, 1935
    - Elections, 1954-1968, undated (Box 10)
    - Electrification, 1931-1938, 1967, undated
    - Espionage
      - General, 1955-1971, undated
      - Powers, Francis Gary, 1960-1965
    - Expulsions, 1956-1970, undated
    - "E" miscellaneous, 1930-1937, 1960
    - Family, 1934-1969, undated, (2 folders)
    - Fashion, 1936-1966, undated
    - Finance
      - General, 1931-1938, 1957-1961, undated
      - Internal loans, 1931-1938, undated
    - Five Year Plans
      - First, 1933
      - Third, 1937-1939, undated (Box 11)
      - General, 1956-1960, undated
    - Food, 1955-1967, undated
    - Food industry, 1931-1937
    - Forced labor, undated
    - Foreign aid, 1956-1967, undated
    - Foreign relations
      - Abyssinia See Container 13, Ethiopia
      - Afghanistan, 1929-1948, undated
      - Albania, 1945-1949, undated
      - Belgium, 1941-1949, undated
      - China
        - Chinese polemics, 1963-1964, undated
        - Clippings, 1927-1972, undated, (4 folders)
        - Communist party, 1963-1964, undated
        - "Daily Review of Soviet Press," 1955-1964, (2 folders)
        - Expulsion of Chinese diplomats, 1963 (Box 12)
        - Miscellany, 1954-1964, undated
        - Negotiations in Moscow, 1963
        - Sinkiang Province, 1934-1935, undated
        - Soviet strategy, 1963-1964, undated
        - Wire service reports, circa 1930s, 1956-1973, undated, (10 folders)
      - Council of Ministers of Foreign Affairs, 1937-1949, undated (Box 13)
      - Czechoslovakia, 1930-1937
      - Ethiopia (Abyssinia), 1930-1935
      - France, 1931-1937, undated
      - General, 1937-1970, undated, (3 folders)
      - Germany
        - Berlin, 1945-1949
        - General, 1930-1935, 1947, undated
      - German-Japanese Pact, 1936-1937
      - Great Britain, 1931-1939
      - India, 1930, 1967, undated, (2 folders)
      - Italy, 1930-1931, undated
      - Japan, 1930-1939, undated For additional material see same container, German-Japanese Pact
      - League of Nations, 1931-1934, undated
      - Manchuria, 1931-1932
      - Miscellaneous countries, 1931-1947, undated (Box 14)
      - Mongolia, 1935-1937, undated
      - Romania, 1931-1935, 1965, undated, (2 folders)
      - Spain, 1937, undated
      - Turkey, 1931-1937, undated
      - United States
        - Americans in the Soviet Union, 1935-1937, undated
        - Communist Party of America, 1931-1937
        - Davies, Joseph E., 1937-1938, undated
        - Diplomacy, 1920-1947, undated, (3 folders)
        - Diplomatic recognition, 1933, undated
        - General, 1940-1969, undated, (3 folders)
        - Meshlauk, Valery I., Vice Chairman, Supreme Economic Council, interview, 1931-1932
        - Soviet press coverage, 1933-1937, undated (Box 15)
        - Trade, 1931-1937, undated
    - Foreign trade, 1931-1938, undated
    - Furnishings, 1954-1957
    - "F" miscellaneous, 1935, 1946, undated
    - Geology, 1937
    - Government structure, 1934-1937, undated
    - Graft, 1956-1957, undated
    - "G" miscellaneous, 1932-1968
    - Health, 1935-1937
    - History, 1937-1938, 1954-1971, undated, (2 folders)
    - Holidays
      - General, 1956-1969, undated
      - May Day, 1935
    - Housing, 1931-1970
    - "H" miscellaneous, 1935-1937, 1970, undated
    - Ideology, 1956-1972 See also Container 138, same heading
    - Industry (Box 16)
      - Foreign specialists, 1930-1931
      - General, 1935-1968
      - Heavy, 1931-1937
      - Light, 1935-1937
      - Stalin Steel Works at Magnitogorsk, 1931-1938, undated
    - Inheritance, 1937, undated
    - Inventions, 1931-1936, undated
    - Jews For additional material see Container 136, University of Wisconsin
      - Birobidzhan, USSR, 1934-1937, undated
      - Emigration, 1972, undated, (2 folders)
      - General, 1935-1973, undated, (4 folders)
    - Journalists
      - Hughes, Alice, 1933
      - Lyons, Eugene, 1932-1933, undated
    - Khrushchev, Nikita (Box 17)
      - Clippings, 1956-1964, undated, (2 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1954-1964
      - Wire service reports, 1958-1973, undated, (6 folders)
    - Kremlin, 1935-1937, undated
    - "K" miscellaneous, 1931-1935, undated
    - Law, 1935-1970, undated, (2 folders)
    - Leningrad, USSR, 1935
    - Libraries, 1934-1935, undated
    - Literature, 1931-1945, undated (Box 18)
    - Marxism, Leninism, and Stalinism, 1931-1937, undated
    - Medicine, 1954-1965, undated
    - Metallurgy, 1939-1947, undated
    - Mineral resources
      - General, 1945-1947
      - Gold and silver, 1931-1937, undated
    - Moscow, USSR
      - General, 1930-1947, undated, (3 folders)
      - Subway, 1934-1937
    - Motion pictures, 1931-1939, undated, (2 folders)
    - Municipal construction, 1945-1947
    - Music, 1930-1938, undated
    - "M" miscellaneous, 1930-1935, 1958, undated
    - Natural resources (Box 19)
      - Fish, 1937, undated
      - General, 1934-1962, undated
      - Rubber, 1932-1941, undated
      - Timber, 1931-1937, 1966-1967, undated
    - "N" miscellaneous, 1930-1937
    - Parks, 1931-1935
    - Personalities, 1946, undated
    - Pioneers, undated
    - Police, 1955-1966, undated
    - Politburo, 1929-1932, undated
    - Political appointments, 1937-1938, undated
    - Politodels
    - Population, 1930-1936, 1972
    - Psychology, 1930-1965
    - Publishing, 1937-1938, undated
    - Purges, undated For additional material see Containers 22-23, Trials
    - "P" miscellaneous, 1931-1937, 1960
    - Radio, 1931-1937, undated
    - Railroads
      - Chinese Eastern Railway, 1931-1934, undated
      - General, 1930-1939, undated
    - Rasputin, Grigori E., death, undated
    - Religion
      - Antireligion campaigns, 1930-1938, undated, (2 folders)
      - General, 1931-1969, undated, (2 folders); (4 folders) (Box 20)
      - Icons, 1930-1932
      - Jews See Container 16, same heading
    - Repatriation, 1954-1964, undated
    - Roads, 1936-1938
    - Russian Far East, 1936-1938, undated
    - "R" miscellaneous, 1930-1937
    - Science
      - Experiments, 1933-1938, undated
      - General, 1946-1947, 1960, undated, (2 folders)
      - Outer space, 1969-1972
      - Priorities, 1930, 1949-1951, undated, (2 folders)
      - Soviet Academy of Sciences, 1935-1938, undated
    - Siberia, 1933-1972, undated (Box 21)
    - Slogans, 1934-1935
    - Social insurance, 1937-1939
    - Socialists, 1956, 1965
    - Soviet autonomous republics
      - Bashkiria, 1941-1948
      - Karelia, 1932-1937
      - Kirgizstan, 1937-1938
    - Soviet republics
      - Armenia, 1931-1937, undated
      - Belarus, 1942-1950, undated
      - Georgia, 1937, 1946-1947, undated
      - Kazakhstan, 1934-1938, undated
      - Tajikistan, 1930-1934
      - Turkestan, 1930-1934, undated
      - Ukraine, 1937-1939, undated
      - Uzbekistan, 1930-1938
    - Speeches, 1932-1947
    - Sports, 1933-1947, undated, (3 folders)
    - Stalin, Joseph
      - General, 1930-1947, undated
      - Interview by Roy W. Howard, 1936
      - Speeches, 1931-1939
    - Standard of living, 1931-1937, undated (Box 22)
    - Supreme Soviet of the USSR
      - Elections and candidates, 1945-1950, (3 folders)
      - General, 1938, undated
    - "S" miscellaneous, 1935-1937, undated
    - Stalingrad, USSR, 1931, undated
    - Taxes, 1935-1937
    - Textiles, 1937-1939
    - Theater
      - Bolshoi Theater, 1934-1938, undated
      - General, 1930-1938, undated, (2 folders)
      - Mei, Lan-fang, undated
      - Meyerhold, Vsevolod E., 1937, undated
      - Moscow Art Theater, 1937-1938, undated
      - Shakespeare, William, performed in the Soviet Union, 1935, undated
    - Trade unions, 1934-1938, undated
    - Trials
      - Bukharin, Nikolai, 1938, undated, (2 folders)
      - Khabarovsk, USSR, trials, 1949-1950 (Box 23)
      - Mensheviks, 1931
      - Miscellaneous, 1935-1954, undated
      - Ramsin, Leonid, 1930-1932
      - Rightist-Trotskyist Bloc
        - Clippings, 1937-1940, undated, (2 folders)
        - Wire service reports, 1936-1938, (2 folders)
      - Zinoviev, Grigorii, and Lev Kamenev, 1936
    - Trotsky, Leon, 1929-1937
    - "T" miscellaneous, 1931-1939
    - "U-V" miscellaneous, 1930-1939
    - Wages, 1931-1938, undated
    - Water transportation
      - General, 1934-1939, undated
      - Moscow-Volga Canal, 1935-1937, undated
    - Women
      - General, 1930-1938, undated
      - Maternity, 1935-1936, undated
      - Matrimony, 1947-1949, undated
    - World War II, 1960-1970, undated, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - "Wrecking," subversive activities, 1937, undated
    - "W" miscellaneous, 1934-1939
    - "Y" miscellaneous, 1935-1937
    - Unidentified